Asaf Mazar

Behavioral Scientist



amazar@usc edu



(714) 323-1108



Los Angeles, CA



www.asafmazar.com



www.linkedin.com/in/asaf -mazar



Skills

Habit and Behavior Change Intervention Science Behavioral Economics Experience Sampling/EMA



Programming

R (expert)
Python, SQL (intermediate)



Statistics

Multilevel Modelling Geospatial analysis Data Visualization Social Network Analysis



Education

Ph.D. / August 2022

Psychology University of Southern California

M.A. / March 2020

Psychology University of Southern California

B.A. / June 2016

(magna cum laude)
Psychology and English
Literature
Ben-Gurion University



About

Behavioral scientist with 8+ years of research experience in academia, industry, and policy. I use applied behavior change expertise and advanced quantitative methods to generate actionable user insights. I enjoy communicating complex ideas to both expert and lay audiences.



Experience

Postdoctoral Research Fellow

The Wharton School at UPenn | August 2022 - Present

Senior Behavioral Scientist

Catalyst Behavioral Sciences | Dec 2019 - Present

- Analyzed consumer data from the U.S., Europe, and Asia, using the resulting insights to shape product development and international marketing campaigns by Fortune 100 companies.
- Collaborated with a team of academic, industry, and policy experts to increase enrollment and retention in a national wellness program (funding amount: \$ +1.4M). Designed and analyzed large-scale studies.
- Data lead on a poll of Christian voters. Worked with non-profit leaders, public relations team, and media editors to communicate poll results in national and local outlets.

Behavioral Scientist

Irrational Labs | April 2021 - *Present*

- Led experimentation to test product features and marketing for both startups and industry leaders. Analyzed data and presented results and recommendations to stakeholders.
- Mentored workshops focused on helping companies leverage behavioral science to increase user conversion and retention.

Graduate Research Fellow / Project Manager (2016-2017)

Habit Lab, University of Southern California | Aug 2016 – Jul 2022

- Directed research teams running complex longitudinal field studies examining habit change and nudges in domains such as exercise, voter turnout, and consumer behavior.
- Used quantitative modeling to analyze multi-method datasets.
- Published original research in top peer-reviewed journals and presented at international conferences.
- Taught undergraduate courses in statistics and research methods.

Selected Publications

Media Coverage

Breaking bad habits: Routines trump willpower. CNN. Aug 29, 2022.

<u>To break unhealthy habits, stop obsessing over willpower – two behavioral scientists explain why routines matter more than conscious choices.</u> *The Conversation*. Aug 9, 2022.

Our Mood Doesn't Affect Our Behavior as Much as Our Habits Do, Says New Research. Forbes. May 29, 2022.

Mood Has Less Control Over Behavior Than We Think. Psychology Today. June 2, 2022.

Could Behavioral Nudges Help us Tackle the Climate Crisis? Financial Times. September 15, 2021.

<u>Trump's Overtures Struggle to Register with Religious Voters</u>. *Politico*. September 10, 2020.

White Evangelicals and Catholics may Finally be Opening their Ears. Washington Post. September 14, 2020.

Selected Academic Publications

Mazar, A.,* Tomaino, G.,* Carmon, Z., Wood, W. (2022). Friction Discounting: Americans Underestimate the Effect of Friction on Voter Turnout. *Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences*.

Haran, U., Mazar, A., Hurwitz, M., Moran, S. (2022). Confidently at Your Service: Advisors Alter Their Stated Confidence to Be Helpful. *Organizational Behavior and Human Decision Processes*.

Mazar, A. Wood, W. (2022). Illusory Feelings, Elusive Habits: Explanations of Behavior Overlook Habits. *Psychological Science*.

Mazar, A.,* Tomaino, G.,* Carmon, Z., Wood, W. (2022). Habits for our Habitat: Using the Psychology of Habits to Promote Sustainability. *Behavioral Science and Policy*.

Wood, W., Mazar, A., Neal, D., (2021) Habits and goals in human behavior: separate but interacting systems. *Perspectives on Psychological Science*.